<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Newfangled Me</title>
		<description>The incoherent musings of Alex Forey</description>
		<link>http://newfangled.me</link>
		<atom:link href="http://newfangled.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>The Art of Typography and its Relevance in the Modern World</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote this piece last summer as part of my English Language iGCSE coursework. After many months of stress and feverish revisions, I submitted it along with a Literature essay and various other small bits and pieces to the exam board, AQA, last Monday. Having done that, I&amp;#39;m free to publish it - and as a few of you have expressed interest, I thought I might as well do so. You better appreciate the styling, becuase I had to write out all the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; elements you can see in the source by hand to get it looking like my Pages document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: the previous typo in the title was not part of the submitted coursework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the invention of the Gutenberg Press, typography has had an enormous influence on culture and has shaped our interpretation of every piece of written language - from road signs all the way up to novels and scientific proofs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to explain further why typography is so important, it is worth mentioning what it is, and what scope it covers. The art of typography is broadly divided into three separate areas: the letters themselves, text as a whole, and the layout of the text. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several aspects to crafting letters, the most important of which is typeface (sometimes also known as font). Depending on the style of document or text being typeset, you’ll need to choose between a serif and a sans-serif typeface. Serif typefaces include small lines that trail from the end of the letter forms, and tend to be used as the body typeface in formal documents or other long-form text. Sans-serif typefaces are mainly used for titles, as well as informational or lighthearted pieces. Typefaces can also be broken down differently, not by their use of serifs, but by their style. Common examples of these include ‘script,’ which is used to emulate handwriting; ‘slab serif’ which has little or no variation between the thickest and thinnest part of the letter; ‘modern’ with large differences between the thickest and thinnest points; and finally ‘old-style’, which is a tribute to the origins of physical typesetting. Finally, there are ‘decorative’ typefaces that don’t specifically fit into any of the above categories - and should not be used for anything other than titles, if at all. There are other variables that can be set when styling a letter, such as weight: the thickness of the letter. Increasing it is often referred to as ‘bold’ in word processors - but in reality weight can also be adjusted the other way. Both &lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 300&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 700&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt; share the same typeface, but at different weights. A thicker letter often gives a heavier and old-fashioned feel, whereas a thinner letter gives a lighter and more modern impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The look of the text can be shaped by several factors that determine the relationship between each letter. Line-height, or the space between lines of text, is also very important in discerning the ‘readability’ of a piece of writing. Thin line-height is often harder to read, but exaggerated line-height can make a paragraph feel more like a series of separate ideas, which can confuse the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, while standard kerning does not have a direct impact on the reader, an &lt;span style=&quot;letter-spacing: -3px&quot;&gt;inco&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;letter-spacing: 8px&quot;&gt; rre&lt;/span&gt;ct ke&lt;span style=&quot;letter-spacing: -3px&quot;&gt;rni&lt;/span&gt;ng can have the opposite effect and disconcert the reader. Kerning is the space between each letter, and is used to stop letters from touching accidentally. It is especially important when designing titles, as the reader does not necessarily ‘read’ the text, but sees the shape of the words and interprets them visually - and thus any discrepancies can throw the reader off-balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have decided on a style of lettering and text, the next important aspect of typography is to consider the layout of the text which tends to be driven by a (normally invisible) grid system. Without you realising it, every time you open a new Word document you create a grid system of a set of margins and one column. Margins are part of a much larger idea of ‘whitespace’, which is another hugely important aspect of typography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;This&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;seems much more important than the rest of the text here because of the amount of whitespace surrounding it, despite the fact that all the text has the same size and weight. A few words with a large whitespace emphasises the type, whereas a large block of text with small margins can be difficult to read and can cause the reader to accidentally skip lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Golden Ratio is a design theory invented by the ancient Greeks, and it was used heavily in the designing of their temples and other buildings. Typography borrows from architecture in its use of this rule, which can be employed to create more pleasing layouts; however some designers claim that it is no better than other methods for creating layouts, and a good design originates more from the size and aspect ratio of the paper used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A grid can also be made up of margins that cross text horizontally, to create space between paragraphs. This type of lateral whitespace is called a hang line, and is commonly used to maintain the flow of a piece where an image is used to illustrate the point being made on the right or left of the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so now you know what typography is, it is worth explaining how it works. Throughout the years, various typefaces have gained a reputation in the industry for their effect on readers, and their characteristics. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;Helvetica&lt;/span&gt; was one of the original sans-serif typefaces, freeing designers from the standards of &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Times New Roman&quot;&gt;Times New Roman&lt;/span&gt; and other serif fonts since its creation in 1957. It allowed the designers to create modern designs for modern times, and is a ‘trustworthy’ typeface, with no frills and no surprises - every letter is consistently designed. It has been used by thousands of international companies over the past 56 years, with variants appearing in the branding of Jeep, American Airlines, Microsoft, Post-It, and even British Gas - and through this use it has become somewhat of a stereotype. To begin with brands used it because of its sensibleness, then others started using it by default, with the result that it has now become severely overused. That is not to say that you should not use it in designs, but you should also be aware of alternatives that could fit your designs better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the opposite end of the spectrum however, we have &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Comic Sans, Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;Comic Sans&lt;/span&gt;. This is a good example of where typography should be used with caution: typography has such an influence on how the reader interprets text that a wrong choice can often be catastrophic. Comic Sans was initially designed for use in comic book speech bubbles, and quickly became popular in primary schools and other children’s literature due to its inclusion in all variants of the Microsoft Windows operating system since Microsoft Bob in 1994. At one point it even had an eye in its &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Comic Sans, Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;€&lt;/span&gt; character. Eventually, however, people started using Comic Sans for all types of documents, driven by its popularity and child-like appearance: hospitals and even governments were using it for official documents. This resulted in serious information being conveyed by a comical typeface. All typefaces have a place and a purpose, and inappropriate use of Comic Sans can mean that people do not take the information seriously, thus rendering the document meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of choice of typeface can be well demonstrated by a real-world example from 2009: IKEA changed their standard typeface. This sort of change is not remarkable in itself; many brands change their branding ‘identity’ often to keep the customers interested and to ‘stay fresh’. Normally customers do not notice or discuss such changes, but in this case everyone had formed an opinion, and there was much argument both online and in other media such as newspaper columns and BBC radio. The general consensus was that &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Futura&quot;&gt;Futura&lt;/span&gt; was a much more elegant and appropriate font than &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Verdana&lt;/span&gt;, which they made the change to. Typography makes up part of IKEA’s public identity, and a switch from a well-established image resulted in lack of consumer confidence, and even a small drop in sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IKEA’s change was mostly decided upon in order to keep their design consistent between their printed information and their website, which had always been set in Verdana. This was because in 2009, Verdana was one of the only fonts that could be used on the web, as it is included by default on all computers. In 2009, new web technologies such as HTML5 and CSS3 had not yet been invented, meaning that website designers could only use fonts that everybody already had. However, in December of 2012, these new technologies were officially standardised, and included a feature called ‘@font-face’. This feature allows web designers to embed fonts into web pages, without the user needing to have them installed on their computers; as well as freeing them from the constraints imposed on them by technology, it allows them to create more diverse designs and fulfil their vision onto the screen. This change is important as, whether we like it or not, eventually print media will begin to disappear as more people move to the web. The extra variety in typefaces that this change allows will encourage people who care about typography to be less sceptical about the web, and to embrace the new technologies associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this change had not occurred, typography would be the limiting factor in people’s appreciation of content online. Now designers can use whatever typeface they want, provided they have the relevant licence to do so - delimiting the influence of typography on modern culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typography has always been relevant to the way people perceive the written word, and with the advent of the web and social media spreading links to articles and information, its relevance is only going to increase over time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 17:53:55 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://newfangled.me/typography</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/typography</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>CreativeBloq Interview</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Following my nomination for a Net Award in the Emerging Talent category, CreativeBloq reached out to me for a short interview over email. They published it on Thursday, along with interviews from some of the other nominations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own head this interview makes me sound fairly sure of myself -- I&amp;#39;m really not -- but I wanted to answer their questions as best I could. There are a few weird things that they left in, like the half sentences at the end of each Little Printer publication description; I was expecting them to edit those into full sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not really expecting to win the award - all the other candidates seem to have worked with more discrete clients than me - but I&amp;#39;m happy to have even made it this far. I know that&amp;#39;s something people say on the X Factor when they&amp;#39;re expecting to lose, but it is nice to have my work put in front of some of the most important leaders in the web design industry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2014 13:51:55 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.creativebloq.com/netmag/alex-forey-working-networked-devices-31411102</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/creative-bloq</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Cloudwash by BERG</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Since BERG finished their transition into being &amp;quot;Cloud services for hardware innovators&amp;quot; (at least for the moment), I&amp;#39;ve been eagerly awaiting their new prototypes that they&amp;#39;ve been hinting at for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, after &lt;a href=&quot;http://bergcloud.com/case-studies/flock/&quot;&gt;FLOCK&lt;/a&gt;, is their next fully fledged internet connected device prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s obvious that a lot of thought has gone into this, and BERG as a company are exploring how the internet will become part of our everyday lives in a unique way. I&amp;#39;m excited to see what they come up with in the future (and what I&amp;#39;ll come up with using my Devshield - I&amp;#39;ve already got some ideas which I&amp;#39;ll post when they&amp;#39;re ready for the world).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2014 17:28:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.bergcloud.com/2014/02/25/cloudwash/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/cloudwash</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Cheapest Android Tablet</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I recently came upon &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dslrfilmnoob.com/2013/12/11/tp-link-tl-mr3040-wireless-field-monitor-dslr-controller/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; on a filmmaking website about how you can turn your Android tablet into a wireless DSLR monitor through the purchase of a $30 battery-powered wireless router.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d been looking for a way to wirelessly control/monitor my camera for a while - partly for events when I want to put a camera somewhere else for a different angle without a second operator, and partly for when I have my camera on a Steadicam (or a cable cam -- more details to follow) and need to monitor my camera without using cables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem was that I didn&amp;#39;t have an Android tablet. At first I thought I&amp;#39;d look at the price of a used Nexus 7, but it was around £80 and I didn&amp;#39;t want to shell out that sort of cash for something like this. iPads can&amp;#39;t do this because of the way Apple locks down developers&amp;#39; access to the Lightning connector, apparently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I conducted an experiment. I looked for the cheapest Android tablet I could find on eBay to see whether it would be up to my needs. I settled on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/NEW-7-DUAL-CAMERA-DUAL-CORE-MULTI-TOUCH-SCREEN-TABLET-PC-ANDROID-4-2-2-br-/301069194415&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; for a whopping £35 with free shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My basic test criteria were: it should be able to run the DSLRController app as it should, as well as being able to provide some light entertainment through Plex, iPlayer/ITV Player/4oD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it arrived. The box looked mostly presentable, and reminded me of the box of one of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Yahui-Player-Media-Music-Audio-Blue/dp/B00GW995TK&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt;, from when I had one before I got an iPod Nano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tablet-box.jpg &quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I perused the back for information was puzzled to see that this tablet usually retails for £99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tablet-back.jpg &quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The specs of the tablet weren&amp;#39;t so surprising any more, given the price it had been intended to be sold at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon opening, I was greeted with a vague attempt at Apple-style packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tablet-open.jpg &quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underneath this layer, accessories had been haphazardly thrown together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tablet-bits.jpg &quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I was pleasently surprised by the tablet itself. It didn&amp;#39;t seem too flimsy, and other than a few stupid design issues like having the power cable come out of the top, it seemed on the whole decent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I booted it up, and after proudly declaring that it was a &amp;quot;Nebula 1701&amp;quot;, it launched straight into Android 4.2.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#39;t go into detail about Android itself, because I&amp;#39;m biased and would never use it willingly in everyday life for anything other than content consumption - but the user experience is as good as I could have hoped for on something this cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my delight, it passed both my tests of functionality: I was able to successfully wirelessly control my 5D Mark III:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tablet-dslr.jpg &quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And watch HD films from Plex once I&amp;#39;d updated my server to the most recent version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I&amp;#39;d say if you don&amp;#39;t want a tablet for anything other than to fulfill a set of basic tasks, this is well worth the £35. Frankly, at that price, you could even just buy one to play around with. If you want to do anything more, however, I&amp;#39;d still recommend an iPad.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 13:00:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://newfangled.me/cheapest-android</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/cheapest-android</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Building My First 3D Printer</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;For Christmas I was fortunate enough to recieve a &lt;a href=&quot;http://printrbot.com/shop/printrbot-simple/&quot;&gt;Printrbot Simple kit&lt;/a&gt;. We got it through an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/Printrbot-3D-Printer-Simple-KIT-/131069073264?pt=UK_Computing_Other_Computing_Networking&amp;amp;hash=item1e84535770&quot;&gt;eBay seller&lt;/a&gt; based in the UK who had stock and fast shipping. At the time of writing, the kit cost £312.75, which is staggering - given how much 3D printers cost only 5 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started building it on Christmas day afternoon and had it finished by the evening of the 27th, with a day off in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://25.media.tumblr.com/4cddc90e957873ec84906a3bbd507068/tumblr_myhoa8dCnc1r3akzno1_500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assembled Printrbot Simple&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could buy the assembled Simple, but that&amp;#39;s no fun - and building one teaches you what each individual component does so it&amp;#39;s much easier to fix anything that breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not going to tell you how to build one, you can find out how to do that &lt;a href=&quot;http://help.printrbot.com/Guide/How+to+Printrbot+Simple/52&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. That walks you through the nitty gritty of getting one formed from the kit as it comes in the box. However, I thought I&amp;#39;d point out a few things that I wished I&amp;#39;d known the first time around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t be an idiot and try to put the M3 bolts through the microswitches like I did. The M2 ones are the tiny thin bolts that are hard to spot in the bag of components unless you empty them out onto the desk. If you do what I did, you&amp;#39;ll deform and shatter the microswitches. Luckily, I found replacements &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.maplin.co.uk/p/miniature-microswitch-with-lever-n96aq&quot;&gt;at Maplin&lt;/a&gt;. At £2.09/each it&amp;#39;s a huge ripoff, but I could collect them at 9am on Boxing Day in person to continue my build as soon as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s definitely worth having some spare zip ties around. I picked up 100 that are identical to the ones that came with the kit for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.maplin.co.uk/p/self-locking-cable-tie-100mm-100-pack-fp16s&quot;&gt;£2.29&lt;/a&gt; on the same outing to Maplins. It&amp;#39;s useful if you mess up and need to cut and redo them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are two nylon spacers in the pack! The smaller one is meant for the filament to go through in the extruder assembly, the larger one is just used as a spacer. Don&amp;#39;t try and cram the larger one into that multi-layer plywood box - it won&amp;#39;t work!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you panic at the end of the build because you appear to have lost the hot end power cable - don&amp;#39;t worry! You attached it to the circuit board earlier as instructed and have since forgotten about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;#39;ve got it assembled, I&amp;#39;d highly recommend reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://joshondesign.com/p/books/simpleguide/text.html&quot;&gt;this 4,000 word epic&lt;/a&gt; about getting your Printrbot communicating with a computer, calibrating it, and finally printing your first somthing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:24238&quot;&gt;first thing&lt;/a&gt; I printed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://25.media.tumblr.com/51b76686b68a131097c797f00292c430/tumblr_myhpy7gQld1r3akzno1_500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;25mm Calibration Cube&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, it&amp;#39;s much larger in the x direction than it should be, and not as tall as it should be. Following the calibration steps outlined in the guide above meant that the next version was exactly 5mm on every step as it should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Wireless Control&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing I did, mainly because I could, was to make the printer run wirelessly over the internet from a Raspberry Pi using &lt;a href=&quot;http://octoprint.org&quot;&gt;OctoPrint&lt;/a&gt;. Usually, you&amp;#39;d have to have your laptop plugged into the Simple for the whole of the build duration - but with this you can upload an STL over WiFi to your Pi and set it going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is super-convenient as it means you can leave the house or do something else with your laptop without distrupting your printing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, if you have a webcam that&amp;#39;s compatible with the Pi, you can monitor your prints remotely and even save timelapses of them. They won&amp;#39;t be of the highest quality obviously (there&amp;#39;s a reason I own a DSLR with Magic Lantern installed), but they&amp;#39;re quick and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Modifications&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are hundreds of modifications out there that people have done on their Printrbot Simples. For instance, Reddit user /u/snickerpleez who &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/PrintrBot/comments/1pkwqa/i_doubled_the_size_of_my_simples_print_bed_for/&quot;&gt;doubled the size of his print bed&lt;/a&gt; for $35 or Elkniwt on Thingiverse&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:121820&quot;&gt;arbitrarily long print bed&lt;/a&gt;, or even this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:97847&quot;&gt;spool holder made from Bic pens&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, here&amp;#39;s a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingiverse.com/JasperJ/collections/printrbot-simple-mods/&quot;&gt;huge list&lt;/a&gt; compiled by JasperJ of all the things other people have done with their Simples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular seems to be placing a glass or aluminium sheet over the plywood to act as a print bed. This makes sure it&amp;#39;s perfectly flat and exempt from the problems of warping. This is the one I plan to try soonest, and apparently a good source of glass is a cheap 6x4&amp;quot; photo frame, of which I have a few lying around unused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, and adding LEDs. Because they look awesome. I spotted a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.printrbottalk.com/forum/viewtopic.php?f=106&amp;amp;t=4066&quot;&gt;good idea&lt;/a&gt;over on the Printrbot Talk forum that I&amp;#39;ll have to try out some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Who&amp;#39;s this for?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have to ask this question, I&amp;#39;d highly recommend you read &lt;a href=&quot;http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2013/08/home-3d-printers-take-us-on-a-maddening-journey-into-another-dimension/&quot;&gt;this great review&lt;/a&gt; of the Simple over on Ars Technica. The kit will take you at least 3 hours of continuous work if you vaguely know what you&amp;#39;re doing, much more if not (some people have taken up to 8). This printer is for hackers and casual 3D-makers. It is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hp3dprinting.co.uk/uprint-se.htm&quot;&gt;HP uPrint SE&lt;/a&gt; that makes perfect prints every time. You will have to spend hours obsessing over calibration and hot end temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that doesn&amp;#39;t sound good to you, then don&amp;#39;t buy this. But also don&amp;#39;t buy a Makerbot Replicator 2 for $2200. That won&amp;#39;t solve your problems. Instead, wait 5 years - and find another hobby in the mean time. This printer is for early adopters and not for the faint of heart. Look at the difference between 5 years ago and now, and think about where we&amp;#39;ll be in 5 year&amp;#39;s time. It&amp;#39;s exciting - I can&amp;#39;t wait to see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2013 18:53:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://newfangled.me/printrbot-simple</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/printrbot-simple</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Behind the Scenes of Gravity</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I was hoping for something a little more in-depth, and that&amp;#39;s probably coming, but for now this 5 minute video gives us a peek into how Gravity was made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of super-awesome motion control rigs and lighting simulation. They make lifting heavy cameras and actors look effortless, which - considering how powerful they are - is hardly surprising, and a little bit terrifying.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2013 16:53:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>http://nofilmschool.com/2013/12/alfonso-cuaron-takes-us-on-a-journey-through-each-stage-of-production-in-gravity/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/gravity</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Twittertape</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I really really want one of these. It should be simple enough once the main mechanism has been figured out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 13:48:55 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.twittertape.co.uk</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/twittertape</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Super-low budget sound equipment</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve got some really exciting projects coming up in the next few months in the small cracks in the blocks of time taken up by my GCSEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of those projects, and for many to come, I&amp;#39;m going to need some (at least) semi-pro location audio equipment, and I saw some great deals on eBay so I nabbed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a brief overview of what I bought and why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B000YCSHG8/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000YCSHG8&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=newfme-21&quot;&gt;Rode NTG-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This microphone is fantastic for the money. It&amp;#39;s not exceptional, but that&amp;#39;s because it costs £160 not £500. It doesn&amp;#39;t produce a very &amp;quot;hot&amp;quot; (strong) signal, so you&amp;#39;ll need some good preamps either in your recorder or externally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds great and full, and I&amp;#39;ll be using it for all my outdoor work (interviews, dialogue, etc). I got it for £100 on eBay including the 10 year warranty which is fantastic for such an inexpensive microphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B000U7B90I/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000U7B90I&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=newfme-21&quot;&gt;Rode NT5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was somewhat of an impulse buy as I saw it for a great bargain (£50) on eBay. I&amp;#39;ll use it for interior dialogue on both narrative work and for conferences, talks, and others. This is because it has a cardioid pickup pattern, so it does not pick up sound reflections from behind like the NTG-2 does. These reflections &amp;quot;colour&amp;quot; the sound and amplify echoes while dumbing-down the intended source of audio when inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also multi-purpose because it can be used to record high-SPL sources, like drums and kicks, as well as violins and other instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B005NACC6M/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B005NACC6M&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=newfme-21&quot;&gt;Tascam DR-40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the cheaper (and better, in my opinion) Tascam version of the Zoom H4N, which is wildly popular amongst indy filmmakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be powered by 3 AA batteries, or via USB from a wall charger or from a phone battery like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B00D5T3QK4/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00D5T3QK4&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=newfme-21&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; which will last you all day and more with a 15000mAh capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tascam has many recording modes for a variety of scenarios. It has two XLR inputs for external microphones which can be recorded together as a stereo track, or additionally with a backup track at -10dB to get you out of trouble if you find the mic clipping unexpectedly. It also has two internal microphones, so you can record 4 tracks simultaneously if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It retails at £185, but look carefully on eBay and you might find it as low as £100 like I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B001IFZEV6?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=3194&amp;amp;creative=21330&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B001IFZEV6&amp;amp;linkCode=shr&amp;amp;tag=newfme-21&amp;amp;=electronics&amp;amp;qid=1377876716&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=rode+blimp&quot;&gt;Rode Blimp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thing is so cool. Not only is it a shock mount that isolates the microphone from vibration and handling noise when on the end of a boom pole, it also prevents wind noise from tampering with your recordings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is so effective that I can literally point an industrial fan at it and there is no wind noise on the recording at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have seen a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rodemic.com/accessories/deadcat&quot;&gt;Dead Cat&lt;/a&gt; before, but that&amp;#39;s nothing to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rodemic.com/accessories/deadwombat&quot;&gt;Dead &lt;em&gt;Wombat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that comes with this thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also comes with a 10 year warranty, and I expect it to be a fantastic piece of equipment for working outdoors with the wind cover, and indoors as a shock mount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got it from eBay for £130, but I&amp;#39;ve seen ones go for as low as £100 is you&amp;#39;re lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Accessories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;#39;ve got all of that stuff, you&amp;#39;re going to need the bits and pieces to put it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my cables from Thomann, Europe&amp;#39;s largest music shop. Sure, you could buy cheap XLR from Amazon, but when you&amp;#39;ve got a nice mic and recorder, it seems stupid to make the link between them weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thomann.de/gb/cordial_ctm_5_fm_mikrofonkabel_red.htm&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; 5m cable for boom pole and general use. It&amp;#39;s red because that&amp;#39;s awesome, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thomann.de/gb/search.html?gk=kamf&amp;amp;bn=Cordial&amp;amp;pr=&amp;amp;kf=on&amp;amp;oa=pra&amp;amp;wgfid1=8137&amp;amp;wgfid2=8577&amp;amp;wgfid3=10330&quot;&gt;any Cordial&lt;/a&gt; will do. I especially like the ones with the Neutrik connectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;#39;ve got the gear I just need to go out and make something with it, which I&amp;#39;m very excited for. I have two short films on the horizon, one of which I will direct and the other I&amp;#39;ll be DP, as well as some shorter projects like Club Drama 2013 (see last year&amp;#39;s one &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/55469257&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you then!
Alex&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 16:53:55 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://newfangled.me/sound-gear</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/sound-gear</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Packing Video & Photo Gear for Holidays</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m going on a trip soon on which I will be taking my video, photo and timelapse equipment, and thought I&amp;#39;d share a brief overview of how I pack my stuff to make sure it doesn&amp;#39;t get damaged in transit or stopped by airport security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, my cameras and lenses go in my Lowepro Flipside 300, along with my rMBP 13&amp;quot;. This is small enough to carry on, and that way I have all of the expensive and breakable things with me at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a Jessops tripod ball head for photography, and a Manfrotto 502AH fluid head for filmmaking. I tend to take both, as they&amp;#39;re not particularly heavy and there&amp;#39;s no point having this stuff if you don&amp;#39;t use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how much I&amp;#39;m carrying in my camera bag, I might put the ball head in there, or in my suitcase. It&amp;#39;s fairly robust and won&amp;#39;t be broken if dropped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My video head on the other hand is what I might call fragile. There are several knobs that protrude from the outside of it that are made of plastic, and are easily broken if not protected properly. I learnt this the hard way on my trip to Nice, where the locking knob for the pan handle snapped clean in half after having been put in the overhead lockers on the aeroplane. Learning from that experience, I take the pan handle and other knobs off the head and put them in my suitcase padded by my clothes to make sure they&amp;#39;re not damaged. I then put the head itself on the tripod in my Manfrotto 80cm tripod bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I&amp;#39;m carrying a slider, I either put it in my tripod bag, or put it diagonally inside my suitcase to keep the carrying weight down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a DIY Arduino timelapse motor and belt system for my slider, which I&amp;#39;ll go into more detail in a later post. An Arduino looks suspicious through airport security, and so I&amp;#39;ve found it best to put the Arduino and cables in my carry-on luggage, and the batteries in my checked-in bag. The staff at Terminal 5 had no problem with this, and through a scanner the electronics look like any PCB they&amp;#39;ve seen before. My suitcase went &amp;#39;missing&amp;#39; when I had the Arduino in it on the way back from Nice, although this may have just been a coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So take care of your expensive equipment, and always carry the most valuable and fragile items with you. This may seem like common sense, but I&amp;#39;ve seen many people put laptops in their suitcases and heard many sob-stories of how that turned out after baggage handling dropped their suitcase 10 meters onto the tarmac.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2013 17:53:55 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://newfangled.me/packing</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/packing</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Little Firefly Publication</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I made another Little Printer publication. This time, it wasn&amp;#39;t a personal project as much, as I worked closely with Firefly Solutions using their APIs and hosting it on their Amazon EC2 instances. I wrote a guest post on their blog, which details what it does.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 13:48:55 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://fireflysolutions.co.uk/blog/the-firefly-little-printer-publication</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://newfangled.me/firefly-littleprinter</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>